until it punctures through. And now the reason why everyone in the operating room was staring at that device on that day was because he had to be absolutely careful not to plunge it through and puncture it into the organs and blood vessels below. But this problem should seem pretty familiar to all of you because I'm pretty sure you've seen it somewhere else. (Laughter) Remember this? (Applause) You knew that at any second that straw was going to plunge through, and you didn't know if it was going to go out the other side and straight into your hand, or if you were going to get juice everywhere, but you were terrified. Right? Every single time you did this, you experienced the same fundamental physics that I was watching in the operating room that day. And it turns out it really is a problem. In 2003, the FDA actually came out and said that trocar incisions might be the most dangerous step in minimally invasive surgery. Again in 2009, we see a paper that says that trocars account for over half of all major complications in laparoscopic surgery. And, oh by the way, this hasn't changed for 25 years. So when I got to graduate school, this is what I wanted to work on. I was trying to explain to a friend of mine what exactly I was spending my time doing, and I said, "It's like when you're drilling through a wall to hang something in your apartment. There's that moment when the drill first punctures through the wall and there's this plunge. Right? And he looked at me and he said, "You mean like when they drill into people's brains?" And I said, "Excuse me?" (Laughter) And then I looked it up and they do drill into people's brains. A lot of neurosurgical procedures actually start with a drill incision through the skull. And if the surgeon isn't careful, he can plunge directly into the brain. So this is the moment when I started thinking, okay, cranial drilling, laparoscopic surgery, why not other areas of medicine? Because think about it, when was the last time you went to the doctor and you didn't get stuck with something? Right? So the truth is in medicine puncture is everywhere. And here are just a couple of the procedures that I've found that involve some tissue puncture step. And if we take just three of them — laparoscopic surgery, epidurals, and cranial drilling — these procedures account for over 30,000 complications every year in this country alone. I call that a problem worth solving. So let's take a look at some of the devices that are used in these types of procedures. I mentioned epidurals. This is an epidural needle. It's used to puncture through the ligaments in the spine and deliver anesthesia during childbirth. Here's a set of bone marrow biopsy tools. These are actually used to burrow into the bone and collect bone marrow or sample bone lesions. Here's a bayonette from the Civil War. (Laughter) If I had told you it was a medical puncture device you probably would have believed me. Because what's the difference? So, the more I did this research the more I thought there has to be a better way to do this. And for me the key to this problem is that all these different puncture devices share a common set of fundamental physics. So what are those physics? Let's go back to drilling through a wall. So you're applying a force on a drill towards the wall. And Newton says the wall is going to apply force back, equal and opposite. So, as you drill through the wall, those forces balance. But then there's that moment when the drill first punctures through the other side of the wall, and right at that moment the wall can't push back anymore. But your brain hasn't reacted to that change in force. So for that millisecond, or however long it takes you to react, you're still pushing, and that unbalanced force causes an acceleration, and that is the plunge. But what if right at the moment of puncture you could pull that tip back, actually oppose the forward acceleration? That's what I set out to do. So imagine you have a device and it's got some kind of sharp tip to cut through tissue. What's the simplest way you could pull that tip back? I chose a spring. So when you extend that spring, you extend that tip out so it's ready to puncture tissue, the spring wants to pull the tip back. How do you keep the tip in place until the moment of puncture? I used this mechanism. When the tip of the device is pressed against tissue, the mechanism expands outwards and wedges in place against the wall. And the friction that's generated locks it in place and prevents the spring from retracting the tip. But right at the moment of puncture, the tissue can't push back on the tip anymore. So the mechanism unlocks and the spring retracts the tip. Let me show you that happening in slow motion. This is about 2,000 frames a second, and I'd like you to notice the tip that's right there on the bottom, about to puncture through tissue. And you'll see that right at the moment of puncture, right there, the mechanism unlocks and retracts that tip back. I want to show it to you again, a little closer up. You're going to see the sharp bladed tip, and right when it punctures that rubber membrane it's going to disappear into this white blunt sheath. Right there. That happens within four 100ths of a second after puncture. And because this device is designed to address the physics of puncture and not the specifics of cranial drilling or laparoscopic surgery, or another procedure, it's applicable across these different medical disciplines and across different length scales. But it didn't always look like this. This was my first prototype. Yes, those are popsicle sticks, and there's a rubber band at the top. It took about 30 minutes to do this, but it worked. And it proved to me that my idea worked and it justified the next couple years of work on this project. I worked on this because this problem really fascinated me. It kept me up at night. But I think it should fascinate you too, because I said puncture is everywhere. That means at some point it's going to be your problem too. That first day in the operating room I never expected to find myself on the other end of a trocar. But last year, I got appendicitis when I was visiting Greece. So I was in the hospital in Athens, and the surgeon was telling me he was going to perform a laparoscopic surgery. He was going to remove my appendix through these tiny incisions, and he was talking about what I could expect for the recovery, and what was going to happen. He said, "Do you have any questions?" And I said, "Just one, doc. What kind of trocar do you use?" So my favorite quote about laparoscopic surgery comes from a Doctor H. C. Jacobaeus: "It is puncture itself that causes risk." That's my favorite quote because H.C. Jacobaeus was the first person to ever perform laparoscopic surgery on humans, and he wrote that in 1912. This is a problem that's been injuring and even killing people for over 100 years. So it's easy to think that for every major problem out there there's some team of experts working around the clock to solve it. The truth is that's not always the case. We have to be better at finding those problems and finding ways to solve them. So if you come across a problem that grabs you, let it keep you up at night. Allow yourself to be fascinated, because there are so many lives to save. (Applause)
hasta que éste se perfora. Ahora, la razón por la que todos en la sala de operaciones estaban mirando ese dispositivo ese día, era porque tenía que ser absolutamente cuidadoso para no hundirlo y romper los órganos y los vasos sanguíneos debajo. Este problema debe parecerles muy familiar a todos porque estoy seguro de que lo han visto en otro lugar. (Risas) ¿Recuerdan esto? (Risas) (Aplausos) Sabían que en cualquier momento la pajilla iba a atravesar, y no sabían si iba a salir por el otro lado directamente a su mano, o si se regaría el jugo por todos lados. Estaban aterrorizados, ¿verdad? Cada vez que hemos hecho esto, se experimenta la misma física elemental que yo estaba viendo en la sala de operaciones de ese día. Y resulta que realmente es un problema. En 2003, la FDA en efecto dijo que las incisiones de trocar pueden ser el paso más peligroso en cirugía mínimamente invasiva. De nuevo en 2009, vemos un artículo que dice que por los trócares suceden más de la mitad de las principales complicaciones en cirugía laparoscópica. Y, ah, por cierto, esto no ha cambiado desde hace 25 años. Así que cuando ingresé al postgrado en la universidad, esto era en lo que quería trabajar. Estaba tratando de explicarle a un amigo, qué era exactamente en lo que estaba invirtiendo mi tiempo, y le dije: "Es como cuando estás haciendo un hueco en la pared para colgar algo en tu apartamento. Hay un momento en el que el taladro termina la perforación de la pared y entonces su hunde, ¿cierto?" Él me miró y me dijo: "¿Quieres decir que es como cuando hay que taladrar el cráneo de una persona?" Y yo le repliqué: "¿Perdón?" (Risas) Entonces lo investigué y supe que los cráneos de las personas también se perforan. Una gran cantidad de neurocirugías, en realidad, empiezan taladrando una perforación a través del cráneo. Y si el cirujano no tiene cuidado, puede llegar fácilmente al cerebro. Ese fue el momento en que empecé a pensar, bien, perforación craneal, cirugía laparoscópica, ¿por qué no, otras áreas de la medicina? Piénsenlo bien, ¿cuándo fue la última vez que fueron al médico y no los chuzaron con algo? ¿Verdad? La verdad es que en medicina, las punciones están por todas partes. Y estos son solo 2 de los procedimientos que he encontrado, que involucran alguna punción en un tejido. Si tomamos solo 3, cirugía laparoscópica, anestesia epidural, y perforación craneana; en estos procedimientos suceden más de 30 000 complicaciones cada año, solo en este país. Yo llamo a eso, un problema que vale la pena resolver. Así que echemos un vistazo a algunos de los dispositivos que se utilizan en estos tipos de procedimientos. Mencioné la epidural. Esta es una aguja epidural. Se utiliza para perforar los ligamentos de la columna vertebral y dar anestesia durante el parto. He aquí un conjunto de instrumentos de biopsia de médula ósea. Estos son usados para excavar dentro del hueso y tomar muestras de médula ósea o de lesiones óseas. Aquí hay una bayoneta de la Guerra Civil. (Risas) Si les hubiera dicho que era un dispositivo de punción médica probablemente me habrían creído. Porque, ¿cuál es la diferencia? Así que, cuanto más investigaba más pensaba que tenía que haber una mejor manera de hacerlo. Y para mí, la clave del problema es que todos estos dispositivos de punción comparten unos mismos principios de física elemental. Entonces, ¿cuáles son esos principios de física? Volvamos a la perforación de una pared. Uno aplica fuerza al taladro hacia la pared. Y Newton dice que la pared ejercerá una fuerza contraria, igual y opuesta. Así, cuando uno perfora la pared, esas fuerzas se equilibran. Pero luego viene ese momento en que el taladro termina la perforación al otro lado de la pared, y justo en ese momento la pared ya no puede hacer más fuerza. Pero tu cerebro no alcanza a reaccionar a ese cambio súbito en la fuerza opuesta. Así que por un milisegundo, o el tiempo que te lleva en reaccionar, todavía estás empujando, El desequilibrio de fuerzas provoca una aceleración, que es cuando se hunde. ¿Y si en el preciso momento de la punción uno pudiera tirar de la broca hacia atrás, oponiendo, en realidad, a la aceleración? Eso es lo que me propuse hacer. Así que imaginen que tienen un dispositivo con una especie de punta afilada para perforar un tejido. ¿Cuál sería la forma más sencilla de tirar de esa punta hacia atrás? Elegí un resorte. Cuando uno extiende el resorte, se extrae la broca y queda lista para perforar el tejido, el resorte halará la punta hacia atrás. ¿Cómo mantener la punta en su lugar hasta terminar la punción? He utilizado este mecanismo. Cuando se presiona la punta del dispositivo contra el tejido, el mecanismo se expande hacia afuera y la asegura en su lugar contra la pared. Y la fricción que se genera, la bloquea en su lugar y evita que el resorte retracte la punta. Pero justo en el momento del final de la punción, el tejido no puede empujar más la punta. El mecanismo se desbloquea y el resorte retrae la punta. Déjenme enseñarles lo que suceda en cámara lenta. Cerca de 2000 cuadros por segundo. Fíjense en la punta. Está en la parte inferior, a punto de pasarse a través del tejido. Verán que justo al terminar la punción, en ese mismo instante , el mecanismo se desbloquea y retrae la punta. Lo mostraré de nuevo, un poco más de cerca. Van a ver la punta afilada. Justo cuando se perfora la membrana de caucho, la punta se esconde en esta vaina roma blanca. Precisamente ahí. Eso sucede 4 centésimas de segundo después de la perforación. Como este dispositivo está diseñado para actuar según la física de la punción y no es específico para la perforación craneal, la cirugía laparoscópica u otro procedimiento, es aplicable a todas estas varias disciplinas médicas en diferentes rangos de longitud. Pero no siempre es así. Este es mi primer prototipo. Sí, esas son paletas de helado, y hay una banda de goma en la parte superior. Esto se hizo en solo unos 30 minutos, pero funcionó. Se demostró que mi idea era válida lo cual justificó el trabajo en este proyecto, los 2 años siguientes . He trabajado en esto porque este problema realmente me sedujo. Me mantenía despierto por la noche. Creo que debería fascinarles a Uds. también, porque, como dije, la punción está en todas partes. Eso significa que en algún momento este también va a ser su problema. Ese primer día en la sala de cirujía no esperaba encontrarme al otro lado de un trocar. Pero el año pasado, tuve apendicitis cuando estaba viajando por Grecia. Cuando estaba en el hospital en Atenas, el cirujano me dijo que iba a realizar una cirugía laparoscópica. Me iba a quitar el apéndice por esas pequeñas incisiones, y me hablaba de lo que podía esperar para la recuperación, y lo que podía a suceder. Añadió: "¿Tiene alguna pregunta?" Y yo dije: "Solo una, doc. ¿Qué tipo de trocar usará?" Mi cita favorita sobre la cirugía laparoscópica viene del doctor H. C. Jacobaeus: "Es la punción en sí la que causa riesgo". Esa es mi frase favorita porque H. C. Jacobaeus fue la primera persona en realizar una cirugía laparoscópica en humanos, y escribió esto en 1912. Este problema ha estado lesionando e incluso matando gente, por más de 100 años. Es fácil pensar que para cada problema importante, existe algún equipo de expertos trabajado día y noche para resolverlo. La verdad es que no es siempre el caso. Tenemos que mejorar en la búsqueda de problemas y en encontrar las formas de resolverlos. Si se encuentran con un problema que los atrape, dejen que los desvele. Déjense fascinar, porque hay muchas vidas por salvar. (Aplausos)